A Finding Aid to the Perry Townsend Rathbone papers, 1929-1985, in the Archives of American Art AAA.rathperr
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1929-1967; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2
  - Lectures, circa 1937-circa 1963; 3.3
    - "Max Beckmann", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Staging the Mississippi Panorama", circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Life on the Mississippi" Drafts, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Inauguration of The Friends of the City Art Museum Group, circa 1952 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "Max Beckmann in America", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "Letters to a Woman Painter", 1948 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Lecture by Max Beckmann.
- Professional Files, 1938-1984; Series 4; 2 Linear feet Box 2-4, OV 6
  Professional files concern Rathbone's directorship of the St. Louis City Art Museum and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, business trips abroad, special projects, and his affiliations with various arts commissions and arts organizations. Rathbone took a "European Trip" every year to view artwork and potential acquisitions for the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. These travel folders include receipts, lists of contacts and hotels, notebooks and itineraries. Also found are documents concerning the George Caleb Bingham drawings dispute, the historic Dederer-Blodgett house restoration, the New York World's Fair "Masterpieces of Art" exhibition, and work done in association with the Massachusetts Art Commission and the Chase Manhattan Bank Art Program. The files hold a range of documents such as correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, inventories, and notes.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by the museum name or project title, and chronologically within each grouping.
  - Boston Museum of Fine Arts Files (Box 2)
    - Congratulations Letters, 1954-1955; 1951 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Critiques by Busch-Reisinger Museum Course Students, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence about Resignation, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Memorandums, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees Annual Meeting Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Board of Trustees Informal Meeting Minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - List of Candidates for New Director Search, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes, 1955-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Raphael Portrait Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Raphael Portrait Multiple Drafts of "Statement of Facts", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Raphael Portrait Multiple Drafts of "A History of Its Acquisition", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Boston Museum of Fine Art Annual European Business Trips (Box 3)
    - 1956 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1957 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1957 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1959-1965 Trips, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1966 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 1966 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1966 Trip, Notebook (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 1967 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 1967 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1968 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1968 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1969 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1969 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1969 Trip, Notebook (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1970 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1970 Trip, Correspondence and Itineraries (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1970 Trip, Receipts (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Boston Museum of Fine Art Business Trips (Box 3)
    - U.S. Trips, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - U.S. Trips, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 1.
    - U.S. Trips, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Russia Trip: Correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Russia Trip: Receipts, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Mexico Trip: Correspondence and Itineraries, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Washington Trip, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - San Francisco Trip: Correspondence and Itineraries, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Egypt-Switzerland Trip: Correspondence and Itineraries, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Egypt-Switzerland Trip: Receipts, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Greek Cruise, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Japan Trip, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Boston Musem of Fine Arts Vouchers, 1955-1961; 7 Folders (Box 3, Folder 43-49)
  - Boston Museum of Fine Art Vouchers, 1962-1970; 9 Folders (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
  - Brooks Memorial Art Gallery 9th Mid South Exhibition, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cambridge Arts Council, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chase Manhattan Bank Art Program (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1965; 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Inventory, circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Draft of Final Report, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Final Report, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967; 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - City Art Museum of St. Louis, 1940-1945; 1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - City Art Museum of St. Louis: "Art for Your Sake" Transcript of Interview with Charles Nagel, Jr., circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Transcript of radio interview with Charles Nagel, Jr. for the City Art Museum's "Art for Your Sake" program.
  - Ford Foundation, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - George Caleb Bingham Drawings Dispute, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 2.
  - Gilbert Stuart Portraits Dispute: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Gilber Stuart Drawings Dispute: Fund Raising Speech, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Gilbert Stuart Portraits Dispute: News Clippings, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Hanns Swarzenski Festschrift, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Historic Dederer-Blodgett House Preservation (Box 4)
    - Engineering Report, circa 1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Sales Contract, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - News Clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Floor Plans, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 3.
    - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Bryden-Trozze AIA, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Infrared Energy Scanners, Inc. Report, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Insurance Policy, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Rental Agreement, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Massachusetts Art Commission (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1968; 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 4.
    - Meeting Minutes, 1965-1977 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Reports, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - News Clippings, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - 1939 New York World's Fair, "Masterpieces of Art" Exhibition (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Lecture, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Printed Materials, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - "Paintings by Horatio Shaw" Exhibition: Copies of Horatio Shaw's Letters, circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Paintings by Horatio Shaw" Exhibition: List and Essay, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Rhode Island School of Design Visiting Committee Reports, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Wellesley College Friends of Art Meeting Minutes, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Oversized Exhibition Poster, 1966 (Box OV 6, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 32.
  - Oversized News Clipping, 1974 (Box OV 6, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 20.
  - Oversized Floor Plans, 1980 (Box OV 6, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 28.
  - Oversized Massachusetts Art Commission Certificate, 1965 (Box OV 6, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 34.
- Printed Materials, 1954-1975; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4-5, OV 6
  Printed materials include press releases, news clippings, bulletins, magazines, exhibition catalogues, articles and event invitations.
  - Catalogue for Exhibition in Memory of Curt Valentin, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - News Clippings, 1954; 1958-1975 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 5.
  - Lee Gatch Monograph, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Press Releases, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Bulletin, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Arts in Virginia, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Arts Magazine, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - John S. Newberry Biography, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in OV 6, Folder 6.
  - Magazine Articles by Perry T. Rathbone, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lee Gatch Exhibition Catalogue, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Programs for Various Events, 1966-1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Event Invitations, circa 1967-1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Skowhegan School 26th Anniversary Dinner Program and Newsletter, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Oversized News Clippings, 1968 (Box OV 6, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 47.
  - Oversized John S. Newberry Biography, circa 1965 (Box OV 6, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 2.
- Photographs, 1936-1972; Series 6; 0.1 Linear feet Box 5, 10 folders
  Found here are photographs of Perry Rathbone and several exhibitions. There is one folder with a handful of portrait photographs of Rathbone. The bulk of the images are of exhibitions including the "Masterpieces of Art" exhibition at the New York World's Fair, a German Expressionist exhibition, and a Max Beckmann exhibition. The exhibitions took place at various galleries such as the Buccholz Gallery, the Curt Valentin Gallery and the Willard Gallery. There is also one photograph of a drawing by Alexander Calder titled "Just 2 Girls from Phillie."
  - Personal Photographs, 1936; 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Masterpieces of Art" Exhibition, New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Klee Exhibition, Buccholz Gallery, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - German Expressionist Exhibition, Curt Valentin Gallery, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Alexander Calder Drawing, "Just 2 Girls from Phillie", circa 1950-1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Max Beckmann Exhibition, Curt Valentin Gallery, circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Curt Valentin Exhibition Photographs, circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Willard Gallery Exhibition, circa 1954 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Buccholz Gallery Exhibition, circa 1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Rathbone Judging Spring Mills 13th Annual Art Contest, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)